Guide to the First Congregational Church of Rushville records,1802-1898.
First Congregational Church of Rushville records,1802-1898
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
First Congregational Church of Rushville records, 1802-1898.
6085
First Congregational Church of Rushville (Rushville, N.Y.)
1 reel microfilm.
Microfilm.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
One volume congregation meeting minutes (1829-1898) dealing with membership and discipline, a pew rent and pledge book (1860-1873), the Church Manual (1869) and Sunday School Records (1820-1824).
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The First Congregational Church of Augusta and Easton (or Eastown) was organized on November 28, 1802 by the Presbyterian missionary Reverend Jedediah Chapman. Later as town and county boundaries changed, it was clled the First Congregational Church of Augusta and Gorham, and by 1868 called the First Congregational Church of Rushville in Yates County. It belonged to the Ontario Association of Congregational Churches and Minsters until that organization dissolved in 1813, and then joined with the Presbytery of Geneva until 1855. On March 20th of the same year, an ecclesiastical Council of Congregational ministers was called to install a new pastor. Twenty-nine members lodged a protest against these proceedings on the grounds that such action was illegal and in contempt of the Geneva Presbytery. Subsequently on May 5, 1855 the church resolved to dissolve its connection with the Presbytery and in 1865 delegates were appointed to the National Council of Congregational Churches.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The records of the First Congregational Church of Rushville, New York are in two parts. Part 1 is church and congregation meeting minutes (item 1-1: 1829-1898), concerned primarily with membership and discipline (not described past 1868). Part 2 contains Related Legal Documents (item 2-1: 1802 1868), a Pew Rents and Pledge Book (item 2-2: 1860-1873), the Church Manual (item 2-3: 1869), and Sunday School Records (item 2-4: 1820-1824). Note that the target sheets for items 2-1 and 2-4 are incorrect; item 2-1 contains a Statement of Incorporation in addition to what is listed on the target, appearing between numbers 4 and 5, and dates for item 2-4 are not June 11, 1820 - June 10, 1821, but are 1820-1824. The Sunday School Records are in poor condition, containing in reverse chronological order 3 entries of annual meeting minutes. In addition, the first 17 pages are illegible.
SUBJECTS
Names:
First Congregational Church of Rushville (Rushville, N.Y.); Chapman, Jedediah.; First Congregational Church of Augusta and Easton (Rushville N.Y.); First Congregational Church of Augusta and Gorham (Rushville, N.Y.); Geneva Presbytery (N.Y.)
Subjects:
Congregational churches--Ontario Association.; Church records and registers--New York (State)--Rushville.; Congregational churches--New York (State)--Rushville.
Places:
Ontario County (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Rushville (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Augusta (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Gorham (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Easton (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Minutes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Part 1
  - Record Book Vol. II, 1829-1898, Item 1-1
    (Vol. I not extant). Church and congregation meeting minutes record admission of new members by letter or examination, granting letters of recommendation and dismission, appointments to committees, hearing committee reports, issuance of citations, censure of members for misconduct, restoration of repentant members to full communion, certification that minutes are examined and approved by Presbytery, yearly sum of members returned to General Assembly, election of deacons, deaths of pastors or deacons, baptisms, delegates chosen for ecclesiastical councils. Minutes are signed by pastor or moderator until 1855 when all entries are made by an elected clerk. After 1855, committee reports are copied in the minutes. Items of note include:
    - p. 3
      Brief history and minutes begin April 5, 1829.
    - p. 11, December 9, 1830
      Member excommunicated for belief in universal salvation.
    - p. 13, March 3, 1831
      Another member excommunicated for same.
    - p. 19, March 7, 1832
      Protracted meeting held.
    - p. 27, May 1, 1834
      Member "rejected" for intemperance, sabbath breaking, and belief in universal salvation.
    - p. 36, January 6, 1838
      Rule adopted re: admission of new members.
    - p. 112, March 20, 1855
      Ecclesiastical Council convened at Rushville. Delegates from other churches are listed.
    - pp. 115-118, March 20, 1855
      Protest by 29 members.
    - pp. 119-120, May 5, 1855
      Dissolution of connection with Presbytery of Geneva.
    - p. 126
      Pagination ends, minutes do not.
    - March 3, 1860
      Temperance Resolution adopted.
    - May 15, 1864
      Committee reports on common fame charges brought against the pastor. Church exonerates him.
    - September 3, 1864
      Pastor resigns.
    - April 30, 1865
      Delegates appointed to National Council of Congregational Churches.
    - Not described past 1865.
- Part 2
  - Related Legal Documents, Item 2-1
    - Articles of Incorporation, November 23, 1802
      Titled "Augusta and Eastown, 1802."
    - Deed, April 26, 1828
      To the southern part of the church lot to Solomon Gilbert Signed by County Commissioner.
    - Agreement, April 26, 1851
      With the trustees of the First Congregational Church and Society and Henry Card.
    - Constitution and By-Laws, adopted 1868
      With names of original subscribers to new meeting house.
    - Statement of incorporation and election of trustees, February 23, 1808
      Signed by County Commissioner.
    - Written resolution, January 1, 1853
      To dissolve connection with Presbytery Presented by moderator of church and congregation meeting.
    - Copy "Original Deed First Congregational Church of Rushville, N.Y.," 1818
      Recorded Ontario County Clerk's Office, Solomon Gilbert to Trustees.
  - Pew Rents and Pledge Book, 1860-1873, Item 2-2
    Lists names, amounts, balance, balance due, etc., with tipped in notes and many loose sheets.
  - Manual of the First Congregational Church, 1869, Item 2-3
    Includes history, articles of faith, covenant, and Standing Rules.
  - Sunday School Records, 1820-1824, Item 2-4
    First 17 pages illegible. Includes students' names, admission dates, assignments, and work completed. Minutes of annual meetings for May 10, 1824, May 1823, and 1822, record election of officers and financial data.